# Simon Liu

Postbaccalaureate Fellow, National Human Genome Research Institute. NIHBC 10 - CRC BG RM 3-2551 10 Center Dr Bethesda, MD 20892

 $\blacksquare$  simon.liu@nih.gov -  $\Xi$  nhgri/medical.genetics.branch

■ simon@simonliu.dev - 🚱 simonliu.dev

github/simonliu99 - orcid/0000-0002-1182-5492

🛅 linkedin/simonliu99 - 🗏 google.scholar

#### Summary

I am a postbaccalaureate IRTA fellow in the Medical Genomics Unit at the X National Human Genome Research Institute, interested in deep learning algorithms that improve patient outcomes. My recent work involves applying natural language processing to genetics datasets to build models for extracting patient and language annotators.

#### Education

**B.S., Biomedical Engineering**, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD.

08/2017 - 05/2021

1-7

Also completed B.S. major requirements for Computer Science Linda Trinh Memorial Award, Joseph F. Strohecker Scholarship

Honors: Upsilon Pi Epsilon, Dean's list, general & BME+CS departmental honors

GPA: 3.69

### Research Experience

**Postbaccalaureate Fellow**, National Human Genome Research Institute, Bethesda, MD. 07/2021 - present With Benjamin Solomon

Software Engineer, Neuroplastic Surgery Research Laboratory, Johns Hopkins University, 02/2020 - 05/2021

Baltimore, MD, USA.

With Chad Gordon.
Received Provost's Undergraduate Research Award 2020-21 [award] [news]

Research Analyst, School of Medicine, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. 12/2018 - 03/2020

With Susan Hutfless

Laboratory Assistant, STAR-ORC, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, 07/2018 - 03/2020

USA.

With Junfang Wu

#### Volunteer Experience

Care Coordinator, Pan Asian Volunteer Health Clinic, Chinese Culture and Community Service 10/2021 - present Center, Gaithersburg, MD.

With Mo-Ping Chow and Yaoyao Zhu

### Teaching Experience

Course Assistant, Department of Computer Science, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, 08/2020 - 05/2021 USA.

With Kwame Kutten

#### **Publications**

A list is also available on Google Scholar and Publons.

Journal Articles

Zhang, Z., Li, Y., Shi, J., Zhu, L., Dai, Y., Fu, P., **Liu, S.**, Hong, M., Zhang, J., Wang, J., & Jiang, C. (2022). Lymphocyte-related immunomodulatory therapy with siponimod (BAF-312) improves outcomes in mice with acute intracerebral hemorrhage. Aging and Disease. [accepted]
Jiang, C., Guo, H., Zhang, Z., Wang, Y., **Liu, S.**, Lai, J., Wang, T. J., Li, S., Zhang, J., Zhu, L., Fu, P., Zhang, J., & Wang, J. (2022). Molecular, pathological, clinical, and therapeutic aspects of perihematomal edema in different stages of intracerebral hemorrhage. Oxidative Medicine and Cellular Longevity, 2022, 1–38. https://doi.org/10.1155/2022/3948921 [pdf]

Hutfless, S., Shiratori, Y., Chu, D., **Liu, S.**, & Kalloo, A. (2022). Risk factors for infections after endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography (ERCP): A retrospective cohort analysis of US Medicare Fee-for-Service claims, 2015–2021. BMJ Open, 12(9).

https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2022-065077 [pdf]

	Sun, C., Han, Y., Zhang, R., <b>Liu, S.</b> , Wang, J., Zhang, Y., Chen, X., Jiang, C., Wang, J., Fan, X., & Wang, J. (2022). Regulated necrosis in COVID-19: A double-edged sword. Frontiers in Immunology, 13. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2022.917141 [pdf]	J-6
	Hutfless, S., Jasper, R. A., Tilak, A., Ghosh, T., Kedia, S., Liu, S., Urrunaga, N. H., Josephson, M., Narang, A., Miller, S., Chen, PH., Joseph, S., & Brant, S. R. (2022). A systematic review of Crohn's disease case definitions in administrative or claims databases. Inflammatory Bowel Diseases. https://doi.org/10.1093/ibd/izac131 [pdf]	J-5
	Ledgister Hanchard, S. E.*, Dwyer, M. C.*, <b>Liu, S.</b> *, Hu, P., Tekendo-Ngongang, C., Waikel, R. L., Duong, D., & Solomon, B. D. (2022). Scoping review and classification of Deep Learning in Medical Genetics. Genetics in Medicine. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gim.2022.04.025 *Co-first authors. [pdf]	J-4
	Duong, D., Hu, P., Tekendo-Ngongang, C., Hanchard, S. E., <b>Liu, S.</b> , Solomon, B. D., & Waikel, R. L. (2022). Neural networks for classification and image generation of aging in genetic syndromes. Frontiers in Genetics, 13. https://doi.org/10.3389/fgene.2022.864092 [pdf]	J-3
	Li, Y., Ritzel, R. M., He, J., Cao, T., Sabirzhanov, B., Li, H., <b>Liu, S.</b> , Wu, L. J., & Wu, J. (2021). The voltage-gated proton channel Hv1 plays a detrimental role in contusion spinal cord injury via extracellular acidosis-mediated neuroinflammation. Brain, behavior, and immunity, 91, 267–283. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbi.2020.10.005 [pdf]	J-2
	Li, Y., Ritzel, R. M., Khan, N., Cao, T., He, J., Lei, Z., Matyas, J. J., Sabirzhanov, B., <b>Liu, S.</b> , Li, H., Stoica, B. A., Loane, D. J., Faden, A. I., & Wu, J. (2020). Delayed microglial depletion after spinal cord injury reduces chronic inflammation and neurodegeneration in the brain and improves neurological recovery in male mice. Theranostics, 10(25), 11376–11403. https://doi.org/10.7150/thno.49199 [pdf]	J-1
Conference Papers	Kenet, A., Mahadevan, E., Elangovan, S., Yan, J., Siddiq, K., <b>Liu, S.</b> , Ladwa, A., Narayanan, R., Dakkak, J., Benassi, T., Ng, K., & Manbachi, A. (2020). Flexible piezoelectric sensor for real-time image-guided colonoscopies: a solution to endoscopic looping challenges in clinic. Proc. SPIE 11315, Medical Imaging 2020: Image-Guided Procedures, Robotic Interventions, and Modeling, 1131520 (16 March 2020). https://doi.org/10.1117/12.2548873 [pdf]	C-1
Meeting Abstracts	Patel, R., Palamuttam, N., Choi, Y., Diamreyan, M., <b>Liu, S.</b> , Park, S.J., Salazar, S., & Goeddel, L. (2021). Intraoperative hypotension before critical care admission is common but not associated with in hospital mortality in non-cardiac surgery. Anesthesia & Analgesia, 132(5S):859-862. https://doi.org/10.1213/01.ane.0000803544.47940.c7 [pdf]	A-3
	Hutfless, S. M., Chu, D., <b>Liu, S.</b> , & Kalloo, A. N. (2020). Predictors of ERCP-associated infections in outpatient hospitals. Gastrointestinal Endoscopy, 91(6). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gie.2020.03.3314 [pdf]	A-2
	Hutfless, S. M., Chen, PH., Miller, S. D., Josephson, M., Joseph, S., Urrunaga, N., Kedia, S., <b>Liu, S.</b> , Arya, N., Hobstetter, L., Persad, P., Yeretssian, G., & Brant, S. R. (2020). Would K50* by any other name smell so sweet? A systematic review of claims-based Crohn's disease case definitions. Gastroenterology, 158(6). https://doi.org/10.1016/s0016-5085(20)31712-1 [pdf]	A-1
Presentations	<b>Liu, S.</b> , Ledgister Hanchard, S., Dwyer, M.C., Hu, P., Tekendo-Ngongang, C., Waikel, R.L., Duong, D., & Solomon, B.D. Applications of deep learning in medical genetics. Poster presented at: NIH Virtual Postbac Poster Day 2022; Bethesda, MD. [poster] [pdf]	P-1
Selected Honors	Outstanding Volunteer Award, Chinese Culture and Community Service Center, Gaithersburg, MD, USA	11/2022
	Awarded at the Chinese Culture and Community Service Center 40th Anniversary Celebration [yearboo	)K]
	<b>Linda Trinh Memorial Award</b> , Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA Project: COVID-19 PPE Manufacturing Proposal: Consortium for 3D-Printed Headbands for Face Shield With Y. Bai, J. Feitelberg, K. Hu, S. Kumar, K. Leo, J. Li, C. Shallal, and N. Zhang	05/2021 Is [blog] [news]
	Intuitive Surgical Best Project Award Runner Up, Deep Learning course, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.	12/2020
	Project: Detection and Segmentation of Pneumothoraces in Chest X-ray. [report] [ppt] [award] With F. Shao, Y. Huang, and A. Harmalkar.	
	Provost's Undergraduate Research Award, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.  Project: Implementing Electronic Beam Steering in an Implantable Ultrasound Device [award] [news]	11/2020
	With Chad Gordon.	
	<b>Upsilon Pi Epsilon</b> , Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. International Honor Society for the Computing and Information Disciplines	10/2020

	Joseph F. Strohecker Scholarship, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.  Maryland Seal of Biliteracy, Maryland State Department of Education, Rockville, MD, USA.	11/2017 06/2017
Selected Press	Stokel-Walker, Chris. "Amid war fears, archivists are racing to preserve Ukraine's internet" Input Mag. February 18, 2022.	2022
	Calabresi, Kaitlyn. "Interview with Health 3D" TCO Labs. November 20, 2019.	2019
	Sangana, Neha. "Conference highlights student startups in Md." The Johns Hopkins News- Letter. November 15, 2018.	2018
Selected Coursework	Computer Integrated Surgery I Computer Integrated Surgery II Machine Learning Machine Learning: Deep Learning Biomedical Data Science	

## Extracurricular Experience

Vice President of Finance, Alpha Kappa Psi, Rho Psi Chapter, Baltimore, MD, USA11/2019 - 12/2020Pledge Educator, Alpha Kappa Psi, Rho Psi Chapter, Baltimore, MD, USA05/2019 - 11/2019Head of Manufacturing, Health 3D, LLC, Baltimore, MD, USA.04/2018 - 05/2021

### Metadata

This document lives online at https://simonliu.dev/cv/.

Foundations of Computational Biology and Bioinformatics

A downloadable version can be found at https://simonliu.dev/files/liu\_cv.pdf.

Based on markdown-cv by Eliseo Papa with styles based on David Whipp.

MIT License.

Last updated: November 8, 2022

Precision Care Medicine I Precision Care Medicine II